Guide to the Paul Ramsey Papers, 1934-1984 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Paul Ramsey papers 1934-1984 and undated
Ramsey, Paul
24 linear feet Extent: circa 14,500 items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
RL.01063
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Portions of the collection are restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Paul Ramsey Papers were received in 1987, 1989, 1999, and 2012.
Biographical Note
1913, Dec. 10 Born, Mendenhall, Mississippi.
1935 B.S., Millsaps College, Jackson, Miss.
1937, June 23 Married Effie Register.
1937-1939 Instructor of history and social science, Millsaps College, Jackson, Miss.
1940 B.D., Yale University.
1941-1942 Assistant Instructor, social philosophy, Yale University.
1942-1944 Assistant Professor, Christian ethics, Garrett Biblical Institute, Northwestern University, Evanston, Ill.
1943 Ph.D., Yale University.
1944-1982 Professor of Religion at Princeton University.
1957 Appointed Harrington Spear Paine Professor at Princeton University.
1959-1960 Vice President of the American Theological Society.
1964-1965 President of the American Theological Society.
1968-1975 Member of the Board of Trustees of Drew University and Trustee of the Council on Religion and International Affairs.
1968-1983 Awarded eight honorary degrees.
1982-1986 Member of the Center of Theological Inquiry.
1988, Feb. 29 Died
Collection Overview
The papers of Paul Ramsey span the years 1934 to 1984. Included are correspondence, memoranda, book reviews, typescripts, reprints, drafts of books and articles, clippings, lecture notes and outlines, course outlines, examinations and handouts, writings of Ramsey and others, news releases, theses and dissertations, and cassette tapes. The principal focus of the collection reflects the direction of the teaching and writing career of Ramsey, principally while a professor in the Department of Religion at Princeton University. These primarily professional papers relate to his major fields of interest: theology, philosophy, and the humanities. In particular, Ramsey's chief specialty as a teacher and scholar has been Christian ethics, beginning with the publication of his classic, Basic Christian Ethics in 1950. There followed writings in ethical methodology, situation ethics, marriage, and sexual ethics. In the 1960s he expanded the scope of his research and writing to include the ethics of warfare and nuclear deterrence, and in the 1970s turned to medical ethics topics, such as fetal research, abortion, and in vitro fertilization.
The Correspondence Series, which comprises about one-half of the collection, and the Writings and Speeches Series form the bulk of the Ramsey Papers. The Correspondence Series consists chiefly of office correspondence including letters from theologians and professors, institutions and organizations, and journals, such as the Journal of Religious Ethics, for which Ramsey served as chairman of the editorial board. Among the correspondents are the American Medical Association, Roland Herbert Bainton, Emil Brunner, Daniel Callahan, James M. Gustafson, Van Austin Harvey, Orrin Hatch, the Institute of Society, Ethics, and the Life Sciences, Henry M. Jackson, Journal of Religious Ethics, Ernest W. Lefever, Richard A. McCormick, Rollo May, Abraham John Muste, the National Council of the Churches of Christ, the National Council on Religion in Higher Education, The New England Journal of Medicine, H. Richard Niebuhr, Reinhold Niebuhr, Richard M. Nixon, Liston Pope, Quentin L. Quade, Warren T. Reich, Eunice Kennedy Shriver, Sargent Shriver, John Edwin Smith, Elton Trueblood, Richard Preston Unsworth, Henry Pitney Van Dusen, and Worldview.
Both the Writings and Speeches Series and the Courses Series reflect the various areas of Christian ethics about which Ramsey wrote and taught. The papers in the Courses Series relate specifically to the three chief areas in which Ramsey taught: religion, philosophy, and the humanities. Of particular interest is the information relating to Karl Barth, especially the seminar on Karl Barth's church dogmatics.
The relatively small Academic and Professional Series relates chiefly to Princeton academic affairs, such as the graduate program in religion and committee work, and The Wesley Foundation. There also is material concerning conferences and programs, such as the Aspen Institute Seminar, the Conference on Life Sciences and Mankind, and Week of Work.
Subject Headings
Princeton University. Department of Religion; American Medical Association; Callahan, Daniel, 1930-; Harvey, Van Austin; Institute of Society, Ethics and the Life Sciences; Lefever, Ernest W.; McCormick, Richard A., 1922-; Muste, Abraham John, 1885-1967; National Council of the Churches of Christ; National Council on Religion in Higher Education; Niebuhr, H. Richard (Helmut Richard), 1894-1962; Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971; Pope, Liston, 1909-; Quade, Quentin L.; Reich, Warren T.; Shriver, Eunice Kennedy; Shriver, Sargent, 1915-; Smith, John Edwin; Unsworth, Richard Preston, 1927-; College teachers -- New Jersey; Theology -- Study and teaching; Christian ethics; Medical ethics; Fetus -- Research; Marriage -- Religious aspects; Sexual ethics; Abortion -- Moral and ethical aspects; Fertilization in vitro, human; Philosophy; Humanities
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, ca. 1939-1982 and undated, (31 boxes)
  - Aa-Am (Box 1)
  - An-Ay (Box 1)
  - Abingdon Press (Box 1)
  - Abrecht, Paul (Box 1)
  - Acheson, Dean (Box 1)
  - Adams, Arthur M. (Box 1)
  - Adams, Harry B. (Box 1)
  - Adams, James L (Box 1)
  - Ahlers, Rolf (Box 1)
  - Ahlstrom, Sydney (Box 1)
  - Air Force Academy (Box 1)
  - Albion College (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Leo (Box 1)
  - Allen, Joseph L. (Box 1)
  - Allers, Ulrich S. (Box 1)
  - Alston, Wallace (Box 1)
  - America (Box 1)
  - American Citizens Concerned for Life (Box 1)
  - American Friends Service Committee (Box 1)
  - American Heart Association (Box 1)
  - American Medical Association (Box 1)
  - American Society of Christian Ethics (Box 1)
  - Americans United for Life (Box 1)
  - Andreini, Paul H. (Box 1)
  - Armitage, Sir Arthur (Box 1)
  - Ashby, Philip (Box 1)
  - Association Press (Box 1)
  - Atlantic Monthly (Box 1)
  - Aubrey, Edwin E. (Box 1)
  - Austin Presbyterian Theological Seminary (Box 1)
  - Ayd, Frank J., Jr. (Box 1)
  - Ba-Be (Box 2)
  - Bi-Bri (Box 2)
  - Bro-Bry (Box 2)
  - Baab, Otto S. (Box 2)
  - Baer, Dee (Box 2)
  - Bailey, Sydney (Box 2)
  - Bailey, Thomas L. (Box 2)
  - Bainton, Roland Herbert, 1894- (Box 2)
  - Baker Book Company (Box 2)
  - Baldwin, Charles A. (Box 2)
  - Balinski, Rebecca H. (Box 2)
  - Barbour, Ian G. (Box 2)
  - Barnett, Das Kelley (Box 2)
  - Barnette, Henlee (Box 2)
  - Barry, Robert (Box 2)
  - Barth, Eugene (Box 2)
  - Barth's Christian Ethics (Box 2)
  - Batchelder, Robert (Box 2)
  - Battaglia, Anthony (Box 2)
  - Battaglia, Frederick C. (Box 2)
  - Beach, Waldo (Box 2)
  - Beacon Press (Box 2)
  - Beecher, Henry K. (Box 2)
  - Beloit College (Box 2)
  - Bennett, John C. (Box 2)
  - Benton, John Keith (Box 2)
  - Berger, Peter L. (Box 2)
  - Bernstein, John (Box 2)
  - Bernstein, Marver H. (Box 2)
  - Berry, Donald L. (Box 2)
  - Berthold, Fred (Box 2)
  - Bertocci, Peter A. (Box 2)
  - Bettis, Joseph (Box 2)
  - Bilbo, Theodore G. (Box 3)
  - Bilheimer, Robert S. (Box 3)
  - Bishop of London (Box 3)
  - Blackwell's Booksellers (Box 3)
  - Blandy, Gray M. (Box 3)
  - Blecker, Michael (Box 3)
  - Bok, Sessela (Box 3)
  - Borowitz, Eugene B. (Box 3)
  - Bossiere, Jacques P. (Box 3)
  - Bowen, William G. (Box 3)
  - Boyle, Ashby (Box 3)
  - Bradley, William (Box 3)
  - Braisted, Paul J. (Box 3)
  - Branscomb, Harvie (Box 3)
  - Branson, Roy (Box 3)
  - Brauer, Jerald C. (Box 3)
  - Brennan, Donald G. (Box 3)
  - Bresnahan, James F. (Box 3)
  - Bridston, Keith R. (Box 3)
  - Brightman, Edgar (Box 3)
  - Brockway, Allen (Box 3)
  - Brody, Baruch A. (Box 3)
  - Bromiley, Geoffrey W. (Box 3)
  - Brosnahan, John B. (Box 3)
  - Brown, Harvey C. (Box 3)
  - Brown, Raymond E. (Box 3)
  - Brown, Robert McAfee (Box 3)
  - Brown University (Box 3)
  - Brunner, Emil (Box 3)
  - Buchanan, Linda (Box 3)
  - The Bucknell University Christian Association (Box 3)
  - Burger, Nash (Box 3)
  - Burrell, David (Box 3)
  - Burt, Robert A. (Box 3)
  - Burtchaell, James T. (Box 3)
  - Buzzard, Anthony (Box 3)
  - Byrne, Brendan T. (Box 3)
  - Ca-CBS (Box 3)
  - Ce-Cl (Box 3)
  - Co (Box 3)
  - Cr-Cu (Box 4)
  - Cahill, Lisa Soule (Box 4)
  - Cahn, Edmond (Box 4)
  - Cain, David (Box 4)
  - Cain, J. B. (Box 4)
  - Call to Concern (Box 4)
  - Callahan, Daniel John (Box 4)
  - Callis, Kenneth R. (Box 4)
  - Camenisch, Paul F. (Box 4)
  - Cannon, William R. (Box 4)
  - Capron, Alexander M. (Box 4)
  - Carmello, Angela (Box 4)
  - Carney, Frederick S. (Box 4)
  - Carroll, Charles (Box 4)
  - Carroll College (Box 4)
  - Cassidy, Robert C. (Box 4)
  - Catholic University of America (Box 4)
  - Center for Policy Research (Box 4)
  - Chadwick, Anthony (Box 4)
  - Chadwick, Henry (Box 4)
  - Chalmers, Mr. and Mrs. A. Burns (Box 4)
  - Charles Scribner's Sons (Box 5)
  - Ch'en, Kenneth (Box 5)
  - Child and Family (Box 5)
  - Childress, James (Box 5)
  - Childs, Brevard S. (Box 5)
  - Christendom (Box 5)
  - Christian, William (Box 5)
  - Christian Action Council (Box 5)
  - Christian Advocate (Box 5)
  - Christian Century (Box 5)
  - Christian Scholar (Box 5)
  - Christianity and Crisis (Box 5)
  - Christianity Today (Box 5)
  - Church Peace Mission (Box 5)
  - Claghorn, George S. (Box 5)
  - Clancy, William (Box 5)
  - Clark, Henry (Box 5)
  - Clark, Roy (Box 5)
  - Coalter, Joe (Box 5)
  - Colenback, Don F. (Box 5)
  - College of Mount St. Joseph (Box 5)
  - College of the Holy Cross (Box 5)
  - Collins, Thomas J. (Box 5)
  - Columbia University Press (Box 5)
  - Commonweal (Box 5)
  - Condliffe, Peter G. (Box 5)
  - Connecticut Medicine (Box 5)
  - Cook, William J. (Box 5)
  - Cooper, Jack (Box 5)
  - Coriden, James A. (Box 5)
  - Corrigan, Daniel (Box 5)
  - Coulson, Robert E. (Box 6)
  - Council for Christian Social Action (Box 6)
  - Council on Religion and International Affairs (Box 6)
  - Crane, Philip M. (Box 6)
  - Crocco, Stephen D. (Box 6)
  - Cross, Frank M. (Box 6)
  - Cross, John (Box 6)
  - Cuninggim, Merrimon (Box 6)
  - Curran, Charles E. (Box 6)
  - Curry, Hiram B. (Box 6)
  - Curtin, Leah (Box 6)
  - Cushman, Robert E. (Box 6)
  - Cutler, Donald R. (Box 6)
  - Da-Di (Box 6)
  - Do-Dy (Box 6)
  - The Daily Princetonian (Box 6)
  - Dallas County Medical Society (Box 6)
  - Danforth, John C. (Box 6)
  - The Danforth Foundation (Box 6)
  - Daues, Vincent F. (Box 6)
  - Davies, Horton (Box 6)
  - Davies, W. D. (Box 6)
  - Davis, Harry R. (Box 6)
  - DeBoer, Lawrence P. (Box 6)
  - Decell, J. Lloyd (Box 6)
  - Demant, V. A. (Box 6)
  - DePauw University (Box 6)
  - Devenny, Joseph A. (Box 6)
  - Devor, Richard C. (Box 6)
  - Dialog (Box 6)
  - Diamond, Malcolm (Box 7)
  - Dietel, William Moore (Box 7)
  - Dietrich, Wendell S. (Box 7)
  - Dillenberger, John (Box 7)
  - Dirks, J. Edward (Box 7)
  - Dix, William (Box 7)
  - Dodds, Harold Willis (Box 7)
  - Doggett, Caxton (Box 7)
  - Donahue, Anne M. (Box 7)
  - Doubleday and Company, Inc. (Box 7)
  - Douglass, James W. (Box 7)
  - Drew University (Box 7)
  - Driver, Tom F. (Box 7)
  - Duesenberg, Richard (Box 7)
  - Duke Divinity School (Box 7)
  - Duke University Press (Box 7)
  - Dunstan, G. R. (Box 7)
  - Duodecim (Box 7)
  - Dyck, Arthur J. (Box 7)
  - Dyer, Murray (Box 7)
  - E (Box 7)
  - Earlham College (Box 7)
  - Ecclestone, G. S. (Box 7)
  - Eckardt, A. Roy (Box 7)
  - Ecumenical Institute (Box 7)
  - Eddy, William (Box 7)
  - Edwards, Carl N. (Box 7)
  - Edwards, David L. (Box 7)
  - Edwards, W. Don (Box 7)
  - Eichhorst, Calvin J. (Box 7)
  - Eliade, Mircea (Box 7)
  - Ellul, Jacques (Box 7)
  - Emory University: Journal of Public Law (Box 7)
  - Encyclopedia Americana (Box 7)
  - Engelhardt, H. Tristram, Jr. (Box 7)
  - Eppinger, Paul D. (Box 7)
  - Evangelische Ethik (Box 8)
  - Evans, Abigail Rian (Box 8)
  - Evans, Donald (Box 8)
  - Fa-Fi (Box 8)
  - Fl-Fu (Box 8)
  - Fagley, Richard (Box 8)
  - Feild Co-operative Association, Inc. (Box 8)
  - Feinberg, Joel (Box 8)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation (Box 8)
  - Felt, James W. (Box 8)
  - Ferre, Nels F. S. (Box 8)
  - Finegan, Jack (Box 8)
  - Finger, H. Ellis, Jr,. (Box 8)
  - Firestone Library (Box 8)
  - Fisk University (Box 8)
  - Flanders, Henry Jackson, Jr. (Box 8)
  - Fleck, James C. (Box 8)
  - Fletcher, John C. (Box 8)
  - Fletcher, Joseph (Box 8)
  - Flores, Albert W. (Box 8)
  - Florida Presbyterian College (Box 8)
  - Ford, John C. (Box 8)
  - Fordham University (Box 8)
  - Forman, Charles W. (Box 8)
  - Fortress Press (Box 8)
  - Fost, Norman (Box 8)
  - Frankena, William K. (Box 8)
  - Franklin, Marvin (Box 8)
  - Fredriksen, Paula (Box 8)
  - Freedman, Benjamin (Box 8)
  - Freedman, David (Box 8)
  - Frei, Hans W. (Box 8)
  - Fried, Charles (Box 8)
  - Frye, Roland M. (Box 8)
  - Ga-Gn (Box 9)
  - Go-Gu (Box 9)
  - Gaffney, James (Box 9)
  - Gardner, E. Clinton (Box 9)
  - Garrett Biblical Institute (Box 9)
  - Garrison, R. Benjamin (Box 9)
  - Garrity, Paul V. (Box 9)
  - Gastil, Raymond D. (Box 9)
  - Gealy, Fred D. (Box 9)
  - George Braziller, Inc. (Box 9)
  - Georgetown University (Box 9)
  - Georgia State University (Box 9)
  - Geren, Paul (Box 9)
  - Geyer, Alan (Box 9)
  - Giannella, Donald A. (Box 9)
  - Gillham, William R. B. (Box 9)
  - Gilman, Richard C. (Box 9)
  - Girgus, Joan S. (Box 9)
  - Goheen, Robert (Box 9)
  - Good, Edwin M. (Box 9)
  - Gordis, Robert (Box 9)
  - Gordon, Ernest (Box 9)
  - Gordon-McCutchan, Robert C. (Box 9)
  - Graber, Glenn C. (Box 9)
  - Graham, George (Box 9)
  - Grant, Robert (Box 9)
  - Graves, Benjamin B. (Box 9)
  - Gray, J. Glenn (Box 9)
  - Green, Ronald M. (Box 9)
  - Grendel, Carl W. (Box 9)
  - Grinnell College (Box 10)
  - Grisez, Germain (Box 10)
  - Grislis, Egil (Box 10)
  - Gross, John O. (Box 10)
  - Grove Books (Box 10)
  - Guess, R. Malcolm (Box 10)
  - Guggenheim Foundation (Box 10)
  - Gustafson, James M. (Box 10)
  - Gustavsson, Roger (Box 10)
  - Gustavus Adolphus College (Box 10)
  - Ha (Box 10)
  - He-Hi (Box 10)
  - Ho-Hy (Box 10)
  - Hall, Cameron P. (Box 10)
  - Hallowell, John (Box 10)
  - Halperin, Morton H. (Box 10)
  - Halverson, William H. (Box 10)
  - Hamilton, Michael (Box 10)
  - Hanus, Jerome (Box 10)
  - Hare, John E. (Box 10)
  - Harkness, Georgia (Box 10)
  - Harned, David B. (Box 10)
  - Harper and Row, Publishers (Box 11)
  - Harrelson, Walter (Box 11)
  - Harris, Joseph B. (Box 11)
  - Harrison, Paul M. (Box 11)
  - Hart, Ray L. (Box 11)
  - Hartt, Julian (Box 11)
  - Harvard University Press (Box 11)
  - Harvey, Van Austin, 1926- (Box 11)
  - Haselden, Kyle (Box 11)
  - Hatch, Orrin G. (Box 11)
  - Hauerwas, Stanley (Box 11)
  - Hauser, David R. (Box 11)
  - Hazelton, Roger (Box 11)
  - Heaton, Richard L. (Box 11)
  - Hebrew University (Box 11)
  - Hedrich, Richard (Box 11)
  - Hehir, J. Bryan (Box 11)
  - Hellegers, Andre E. (Box 11)
  - Helms, Jesse (Box 11)
  - Hendel, Charles W. (Box 11)
  - Henle, Robert J. (Box 11)
  - Henry, Stuart C. (Box 11)
  - Hertwig, Fred A. (Box 11)
  - Hesburgh, Theodore M. (Box 11)
  - Heyer, George S. (Box 11)
  - Hick, John H. (Box 11)
  - Higgins, George G. (Box 11)
  - Historical Evaluation and Research Organization (HERO) (Box 11)
  - Hjelm, Norman A. (Box 11)
  - Holbrook, Clyde A. (Box 11)
  - Hollenbach, David (Box 11)
  - Holman, Edwin J. (Box 11)
  - Holmer, Paul (Box 12)
  - Holt, Rinehart and Winston Publishers (Box 12)
  - Homrighause, E. G. (Box 12)
  - Hopkins, C. Howard (Box 12)
  - Horan, Dennis J. (Box 12)
  - Horne, David (Box 12)
  - Howard, John A. (Box 12)
  - Howard University (Box 12)
  - Hucker, Bruce (Box 12)
  - Hudnut, William H., III (Box 12)
  - Hudson Institute (Box 12)
  - Hunt, George L. (Box 12)
  - Hurwitz, Francis L. (Box 12)
  - Hutchens, John K. (Box 12)
  - I (Box 12)
  - Institute of Religion (Box 12)
  - Institute of Society, Ethics and the Life Sciences. Hastings Center (Box 12)
  - Interfaith Association of Bryn Mawr (Box 12)
  - J (Box 12)
  - Jackson, Gordon E. (Box 12)
  - Jackson, Henry Martin, 1912- (Box 12)
  - Jackson Academy of Medicine (Box 12)
  - Jamison, Leland (Box 12)
  - Jefferson, H. B. (Box 12)
  - Johnson, Douglas (Box 12)
  - Johnson, James T. (Box 13)
  - Jonas, Hans (Box 13)
  - Jones, Howard Henry W. (Box 13)
  - Jones, M. J. (Box 13)
  - Jones, W. Paul (Box 13)
  - The Joseph P. Kennedy Foundation (Box 13)
  - Journal of Medicine and Philosophy (Box 13)
  - Journal of Religion (Box 13)
  - Journal of Religious Ethics (Box 13)
  - Joynt, Carey B. (Box 13)
  - Judd, Charles M. (Box 13)
  - Ka-Ke (Box 13)
  - Kh-Ku (Box 13)
  - Kass, Leon (Box 13)
  - Katz, Howard C. (Box 13)
  - Kaufman, Gordon D. (Box 13)
  - Kaufmann, Fritz (Box 13)
  - Kee, Howard (Box 14)
  - Kegley, Charles W. (Box 14)
  - Keim, James A. (Box 14)
  - Kennan, George (Box 14)
  - Key, David Martin (Box 14)
  - Kimball, John T. (Box 14)
  - Kimnach, Wilson H. (Box 14)
  - King, Thomas J. (Box 14)
  - King's College (Box 14)
  - Kippley, John F. (Box 14)
  - Kirkland, William H. (Box 14)
  - Kneen, Brewster (Box 14)
  - Knox, John (Box 14)
  - Koinonia Society, Princeton Theological Seminary (Box 14)
  - Kolbe, Henry E. (Box 14)
  - Koziol, Geoffrey (Box 14)
  - Kroner, Richard (Box 14)
  - Kukin, Marrick (Box 14)
  - Kuntz, Paul (Box 14)
  - La-Le (Box 14)
  - Li-Lov (Box 14)
  - Low-Ly (Box 14)
  - Lacy, Creighton (Box 14)
  - Ladimer, Irving (Box 14)
  - Langford, Thomas Anderson, 1929- (Box 14)
  - Latourette, Kenneth Scott (Box 14)
  - Lawler, Justus George (Box 14)
  - Lazareth, William H. (Box 14)
  - Lebacqz, Karen (Box 14)
  - Lefever, Ernest W. (Box 15)
  - Lefever Testimony (Box 15)
  - Lehmann, Paul (Box 15)
  - Leith, John H. (Box 15)
  - Lemonick, Aaron (Box 15)
  - Lewis, Frank Bell (Box 15)
  - Lieb, Irwin C. (Box 15)
  - Lindsley, Karen (Box 15)
  - Littell, Franklin H. (Box 15)
  - Little, David (Box 15)
  - Loder, Theodore W. (Box 15)
  - Long, Charles (Box 15)
  - Long, Edward L., Jr. (Box 15)
  - Longsworth, William (Box 15)
  - Loomer, Bernard M. (Box 15)
  - Love, Thomas (Box 15)
  - Lovett, Sidney (Box 15)
  - Lucas, George (Box 15)
  - Lutheran Church (Box 15)
  - Lynn, Robert W. (Box 15)
  - Lyons, Gene M. (Box 15)
  - Mc (Box 16)
  - Ma (Box 16)
  - Me-Mi (Box 16)
  - Mo-My (Box 16)
  - Macaulay, Sid (Box 16)
  - McClellan, Myron (Box 16)
  - McCollough, Thomas E. (Box 16)
  - McCord, James I. (Box 16)
  - McCormick, Richard A. (Box 16)
  - McEllhenney, John G. (Box 17)
  - McGill, Arthur C. (Box 17)
  - McGill University (Box 17)
  - McGreal, Ian P. (Box 17)
  - McHugh, James T. (Box 17)
  - McKeever, Paul E. (Box 17)
  - Macmillan Company (Box 17)
  - Macquarrie, John (Box 17)
  - Maddy, Joseph (Box 17)
  - Maggi, Richard P. (Box 17)
  - Maguire, Dan (Box 17)
  - Malloy, Edward (Box 17)
  - Man and Medicine (Box 17)
  - Manschreck, Clyde (Box 17)
  - Mansell, Marion E. (Box 17)
  - Marker, Charles (Box 17)
  - Martin, J. Alfred (Box 17)
  - Martin, James A. (Box 17)
  - Marxsen, Roger (Box 17)
  - May, Rollo, 1909- (Box 17)
  - May, William E. (Box 17)
  - May, William Francis (Box 17)
  - Medical University of South Carolina (Box 17)
  - Meeks, Wayne A. (Box 17)
  - Meilaender, Gilbert Carl (Box 17)
  - Meitzen, Manfred O. (Box 17)
  - Menking, Stanley J. (Box 17)
  - Menninger, Karl Augustus (Box 17)
  - Meridian Books, Inc. (Box 17)
  - Mestres, Ricardo A. (Box 17)
  - Methodist Church (Box 18)
  - Methodists for Life (Box 18)
  - Michaelsen, Robert (Box 18)
  - Mickey, Robert G. (Box 18)
  - Miller, Donald G. (Box 18)
  - Miller, Perry (Box 18)
  - Miller, William Lee (Box 18)
  - Millsaps College (Box 18)
  - Minear, Paul S. (Box 18)
  - Mitchell, Basil (Box 18)
  - Monk, Robert C. (Box 18)
  - Moore, Anthony R. (Box 18)
  - Moore, Francis D. (Box 18)
  - Moore, Maurice J. (Box 18)
  - Moore, Ross (Box 18)
  - Morgan, Alfred P. (Box 18)
  - Morgan, Kenneth (Box 18)
  - Motive Magazine (Box 18)
  - Mount Holyoke College (Box 18)
  - Mudge, Lewis Seymour (Box 18)
  - Muelder, Walter G. (Box 18)
  - Mueller, William (Box 18)
  - Muhlenberg College (Box 18)
  - Muilenburg, James (Box 18)
  - Mullooly, John P. (See also National Federation of Catholic Physicians' Guilds) (Box 18)
  - Murchison, D. Cameron, Jr. (Box 18)
  - Murphy, Roland E. (Box 18)
  - Murray, Andrew E. (Box 18)
  - Murray, John Courtney (Box 18)
  - Muste, A. J. (Box 18)
  - N (Box 19)
  - Nagle, William J. (Box 19)
  - National Academy of Sciences (Box 19)
  - National Broadcasting Company, Inc. (Box 19)
  - National Council of the Churches of Christ (Box 19)
  - National Council on Religion in Higher Education (Box 19)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (Box 19)
  - National Federation of Catholic Physicians' Guilds (See also Mullooly, John P.) (Box 19)
  - National Right to Life (Box 19)
  - National Transplant Information Center (Box 19)
  - Nelson, Harold R. (Box 19)
  - Nelson, J. Robert (Box 19)
  - Nelson, Paul (Box 19)
  - Nesbitt, C. F. (Box 19)
  - Neuhaus, Richard John (Box 19)
  - Neusner, Jack (Box 19)
  - New American Library (Box 19)
  - The New England Journal of Medicine (Box 19)
  - New York Herald Tribune Book Review (Box 19)
  - New York Times (Box 19)
  - New York University: Law Review (Box 20)
  - New York University School of Law (Box 20)
  - Newscope (Box 20)
  - Newsday (Box 20)
  - Newton, Rachel Abraham (Box 20)
  - Nichols, James H. (Box 20)
  - Niebuhr, H. Richard (Helmut Richard) (Box 20)
  - Niebuhr (H. Richard) Volume (Box 20)
  - Niebuhr, Reinhold (Box 20)
  - Niebuhr, Richard R. (Box 20)
  - Nielsen, Niels C., Jr. (Box 20)
  - Nixon, Richard M. (Box 20)
  - Norm and Context in Christian Ethics (2 folders) (See also Writings and Speeches Series ) (Box 20)
  - Northwestern College (Box 20)
  - Northwestern University (Box 20)
  - Novak, Michael (Box 20)
  - Nuclear War Institute (Box 20)
  - O (Box 20)
  - Oates, Whitney J. (Box 21)
  - Oberlin College (Box 21)
  - O'Brien, Edwin F. (Box 21)
  - O'Brien, William V. (Box 21)
  - O'Conner, Donald (Box 21)
  - O'Connor, Joseph A. (Box 21)
  - Oden, Thomas C. (Box 21)
  - O'Donovan, Oliver (Box 21)
  - Ogden, Schubert M. (Box 21)
  - Olds, Glenn A. (Box 21)
  - Oliver and Boyd Publishers (Box 21)
  - Ostertag, Frank R. (Box 21)
  - Ostling, Richard (Box 21)
  - Outka, Gene (Box 21)
  - Outler, Albert C. (Box 21)
  - Oxford University Press (Box 21)
  - Oxnam, Robert Fisher (Box 21)
  - Pa-Pe (Box 21)
  - Pf-Py (Box 21)
  - P. F. Collier and Son Corporation (Box 21)
  - Pacific School of Religion (Box 21)
  - Paffrath, Leslie (Box 21)
  - Pagels, Elaine H. (Box 21)
  - Painter, John D. (Box 21)
  - Parke, David B. (Box 21)
  - Pelikan, Jaroslav Jan (Box 21)
  - Penzel, Klaus (Box 21)
  - Percy, Charles Harting (Box 21)
  - Perkins, Robert L. (Box 22)
  - Peteet, Dennie R. (Box 22)
  - Pfuetze, Paul E. (Box 22)
  - Phillips, James (Box 22)
  - Philosophy Forum (Box 22)
  - Pittsburgh Festival on the Gospels (Box 22)
  - Pittsburgh-Xenia Theological Seminary (Box 22)
  - Platt, Michael (Box 22)
  - Pope, Liston (Box 22)
  - Porter, Otto (Box 22)
  - Postgraduate Medicine (Box 22)
  - Potter, Ralph B. (Box 22)
  - The Prairie School (Box 22)